So, I have a feature on my website where every week
لدي خاصية في موقعي، حيث في كل أسبوع
people submit hypothetical questions
يطرح علي الناس أسئلة فرضية
for me to answer,
لأجيبهم عليها،
and I try to answer them using math, science
وأحاول الإجابة عليها باستخدام الحساب والعلوم
and comics.
والرسوم الهزلية.
So for example, one person asked,
فمثلًا، سألني شخص ما،
what would happen if you tried to hit a baseball
ما الذي سيحدث لو حاولت ضرب كرة بيسبول
pitched at 90 percent of the speed of light?
منطلقة بـسرعة 90% من سرعة الضوء؟
So I did some calculations.
فقمت ببعض الحسابات.
Now, normally, when an object flies through the air,
عادةً، عندما يطير جسم في الهواء،
the air will flow around the object,
فإن تيار الهواء يسري حوله،
but in this case, the ball would be going so fast
لكن في هذه الحالة، ستكون الكرة منطلقة بسرعة عالية
that the air molecules wouldn't have time
حيث أن جزيئات الهواء لن يكون لديها وقت
to move out of the way.
لتبتعد عن طريق الكرة.
The ball would smash right into and through them,
فستصطدم الكرة بها وتعبر من خلالها،
and the collisions with these air molecules
وهذا الاصطدام مع جزيئات الهواء
would knock away the nitrogen,
سيسلب النيتروجين،
carbon and hydrogen from the ball,
والكربون والهيدروجين من الكرة،
fragmenting it off into tiny particles,
مجزءً إياها إلى قطع صغيرة جدًا،
and also triggering waves of thermonuclear fusion
وكذلك سيحفز موجات حرارية نووية صاهرة
in the air around it.
حول الهواء المحيط بها.
This would result in a flood of x-rays
هذا سينتج فائض من الأشعة السينية
that would spread out in a bubble
ستكبر على شكل فقاعة
along with exotic particles,
مع أجسام غريبة أخرى،
plasma inside, centered on the pitcher's mound,
ستكون البلازما في وسط ركام الرمية،
and that would move away from the pitcher's mound
وستبتعد كذلك عن ركام الرمية
slightly faster than the ball.
أسرع قليلًا من الكرة نفسها.
Now at this point, about 30 nanoseconds in,
وفي هذه اللحظة وحوالي 30 نانو ثانية،
the home plate is far enough away
سيكون موقع ضارب الكرة بعيد بما يكفي
that light hasn't had time to reach it,
لدرجة أن الضوء ليس لديه وقت كاف ليصل إليه
which means the batter
مما يعني أن الرامي
still sees the pitcher about to throw
لا يزال يرى الكرة ترمى باتجاهه
and has no idea that anything is wrong.
وليس لديه فكرة بأن شي سئ على وشك الحدوث.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, after 70 nanoseconds,
والآن وبعد 70 نانو ثانية،
the ball will reach home plate,
ستصل الكرة إلى موقع الضارب،
or at least the cloud of expanding plasma
أو على الأقل سحابة البلازما المتضخمة
that used to be the ball,
التي كان يفترض أن تكون الكرة
and it will engulf the bat and the batter
وستلتهم المضرب والضارب
and the plate and the catcher and the umpire
وصفيحة الموقع والملتقط والحكم
and start disintegrating them all
وستبدأ في تحليلهم جميعًا
as it also starts to carry them backward
أيضًا ستبدأ في سحبهم للخلف
through the backstop, which also starts to disintegrate.
إلى نقطة النهاية التي بدأت أيضًا في التحلل.
So if you were watching this whole thing
فلو كنتم تشاهدون ماجرى بالكامل،
from a hill,
من فوق تل ما،
ideally, far away,
من المثالي أن يكون بعيد جدًا،
what you'd see is a bright flash of light
ما يفترض أن ترونه هو بريق ساطع من النور
that would fade over a few seconds,
يختفي خلال ثواني،
followed by a blast wave spreading out,
يتبعه موجة إنفجار تنتشر
shredding trees and houses
لتحطم الأشجار والمنازل
as it moves away from the stadium,
أثناء ابتعادها عن ملعب البيسبول،
and then eventually a mushroom cloud
وفي النهاية ستظهر سحابة فطرية الشكل
rising up over the ruined city. (Laughter)
تعلو حطام المدينة. (ضحك)
So the Major League Baseball rules
مع أن قوانين دوري البيسبول
are a little bit hazy,
غامضة إلى حد ما،
but — (Laughter) — under rule 6.02 and 5.09,
لكن، (ضحك)، استنادًا للقانون رقم 6.02 و 5.09،
I think that in this situation,
فإنه في هذه الحالة،
the batter would be considered hit by pitch
سيعتبر أن الضارب قد ضُرب برمية
and would be eligible to take first base,
وسيكون جديرًا بالركض للنقطة الأولى،
if it still existed.
هذا في حال أنها مازالت موجودة.
So this is the kind of question I answer,
هذه هي نوعية الأسئلة التي أجيب عليها،
and I get people writing in with
يكتب لي الناس المزيد
a lot of other strange questions.
من الأسئلة الغريبة الأخرى.
I've had someone write and say,
مثلًا كتب لي شخص ما يقول،
scientifically speaking, what is the best
علميًا، ماهي أفضل وأسرع
and fastest way to hide a body?
طريقة لإخفاء جثة؟
Can you do this one soon?
هل من الممكن أن تستعجل قليلًا في الرد؟
And I had someone write in,
هناك شخص آخر كتب لي،
I've had people write in about,
والكثير من الناس يكتبون لي عن،
can you prove whether or not you can find love again
هل يمكنك إثبات القدرة على الحب مرة أخرى
after your heart's broken?
بعد أن جرح قلبك؟
And I've had people send in
هناك ناس آخرين يرسلون لي
what are clearly homework questions
أسئلة من الواضح أنها واجباتهم المنزلية
they're trying to get me to do for them.
ويريدون مني أن أؤديها عنهم.
But one week, a couple months ago,
لكن في مرة ما وقبل عدة أشهر،
I got a question that was actually about Google.
استلمت سؤالًا كان عن غوغل.
If all digital data in the world were stored on punch cards,
لو كانت كل المعلومات في العالم مخزنة على بطاقات مثقبة،
how big would Google's data warehouse be?
كم ستكون سعة مستودع غوغل للبيانات؟
Now, Google's pretty secretive about their operations,
وبما أن غوغل متحفظة جدًا على أعمالها،
so no one really knows how much data Google has,
فلا أحد يعلم كمّ البيانات التي لدى غوغل،
and in fact, no one really knows how many data centers Google has,
في الحقيقة، لا أحد يعلم كم مركز بيانات لدى غوغل،
except people at Google itself.
ما عدا موظفي غوغل أنفسهم.
And I've tried, I've met them a few times,
وقد حاولت أن ألتقي بهم عدة مرات،
tried asking them, and they aren't revealing anything.
حاولت أن أسألهم، لكنهم لم يطلعوني على أي شئ
So I decided to try to figure this out myself.
لذلك قررت أن أكتشف الجواب بنفسي.
There are a few things that I looked at here.
هناك عدة أشياء ركزت عليها هنا.
I started with money.
بدأت بالمال.
Google has to reveal how much they spend,
على غوغل أن تعرض مقدار ما أنفقته بشكل عام،
in general, and that lets you put some caps
ذلك يسمح لك بأن تخمن
on how many data centers could they be building,
كم هي مراكز البيانات التي يبنونها،
because a big data center costs a certain amount of money.
لأن مراكز البيانات تكلف مقدار معين من المال.
And you can also then put a cap on
بعدها تستطيع أن تخمن أيضًا
how much of the world hard drive market are they taking up,
كم كمية استهلاكهم من الأقراص الصلبة،
which turns out, it's pretty sizable.
والتي اتضح بأنها ضخمة جدًا.
I read a calculation at one point,
وقد قرأت حسابا،
I think Google has a drive failure
بأن غوغل لديها خلل في الأقراص الصلبة
about every minute or two,
حوالي كل دقيقة أو دقيقتين،
and they just throw out the hard drive
فيقومون برمي ذلك القرص
and swap in a new one.
واستبداله بآخر جديد.
So they go through a huge number of them.
بالتالي سيكون استهلاكهم منها ضخم جدًا.
And so by looking at money,
بالتركيز على المال،
you can get an idea of how many of these centers they have.
سيصبح لدينا فكرة عن عدد مراكز بياناتهم.
You can also look at power.
يمكننا أيضًا النظر إلى استهلاك الكهرباء.
You can look at how much electricity they need,
فلو نظرنا إلى كمية الكهرباء التي يحتاجونها،
because you need a certain amount of electricity to run the servers,
لأنهم يحتاجون استهلاك معين من الكهرباء لتشغيل الخوادم،
and Google is more efficient than most,
وغوغل أكفأ من غيرها،
but they still have some basic requirements,
إلا أنه يظل لديها بعض المتطلبات الأساسية،
and that lets you put a limit
وذلك يجعلك تضع حدًا بالاعتماد
on the number of servers that they have.
على عدد الخوادم لديهم.
You can also look at square footage and see
بإمكانك أيضًا أن تنظر إلى المساحة المربعة
of the data centers that you know,
لترى بالنسبة لمركز البيانات التي لديك،
how big are they?
وتخمن ماهو كبرها؟
How much room is that?
وكم تبلغ مساحتها؟
How many server racks could you fit in there?
كم هي رفوف الخوادم التي تتسع لها؟
And for some data centers,
بالنسبة لبعض مراكز البيانات،
you might get two of these pieces of information.
ممكن أن تتحصل على معلومتين عنها.
You know how much they spent,
قد تعرف كم مقدار ما ينفقون،
and they also, say, because they had to contract
ولأنه عليهم كذلك التعاقد
with the local government
مع الحكومة المحلية
to get the power provided,
لتزودهم بالطاقة،
you might know what they made a deal to buy,
قد تعرف أيضًا صفقاتهم وماذا سيشترون
so you know how much power it takes.
وبالتالي ستعرف حجم الطاقة التي يحتاجونها لذلك.
Then you can look at the ratios of those numbers,
وبالنظر إلى معدل تلك الأرقام
and figure out for a data center
تستطيع التخمين بالنسبة للمراكز التي
where you don't have that information,
ليس لديك معلومات عنها،
you can figure out,
تستطيع معرفة،
but maybe you only have one of those,
قد يكون لديك معلومة واحدة فقط،
you know the square footage, then you could figure out
مثلًا بمعرفتك للمساحة المربعة، يمكنك معرفة
well, maybe the power is proportional.
حسنًا، قد تكون الطاقة نسبية.
And you can do this same thing with a lot of different quantities,
تستطيع عمل نفس الشئ مع كميات كبيرة مختلفة،
you know, with guesses about the total amount of storage,
بتخمين كميات التخزين الإجمالية،
the number of servers, the number of drives per server,
عدد الخوادم وعدد الأقراص لكل خادم،
and in each case using what you know
وفي كل حالة تستخدم ما تعرفه
to come up with a model that narrows down
لتستنتج نموذجا يقلل من احتمالات
your guesses for the things that you don't know.
تخمينك للأشياء التي لا تعرفها.
It's sort of circling around the number you're trying to get.
إنه نوع من الدوران حول الرقم الذي تحاول الوصول إليه.
And this is a lot of fun.
وهذا ممتع للغاية.
The math is not all that advanced,
المسائل الحسابية ليست معقدة جدًا،
and really it's like nothing more than
في الحقيقة ليس سوى شئ يشبه
solving a sudoku puzzle.
حل لعبة سودوكو.
So what I did, I went through all of this information,
حسنًا ما الذي فعلته، قمت بالتعامل مع كل هذه المعلومات،
spent a day or two researching.
أمضيت يومًا أو اثنين في البحث.
And there are some things I didn't look at.
هناك بعض الأشياء لم ألتفت لها.
You could always look at the Google
بإمكانكم دائمًا النظر إلى
recruitment messages that they post.
إعلانات التوظيف لغوغل
That gives you an idea of where they have people.
قد تعطيك فكرة عن مكان تواجد موظفيهم.
Sometimes, when people visit a data center,
أحيانًا، عندما يزور الناس مراكز البيانات،
they'll take a cell-cam photo and post it,
فإنهم يلتقطون صورة بهاتفهم وينشرونها،
and they aren't supposed to,
مع أنه لا يفترض بهم فعل ذلك،
but you can learn things about their hardware that way.
لكنك قد تعرف شيئًا عن عتادهم من خلال تلك الطريقة.
And in fact, you can just look at pizza delivery drivers.
في الواقع، بإمكانك مراقبة موظفي توصيل البيتزا.
Turns out, they know where all the Google data centers are,
من الواضح أنهم يعرفون أماكن كل مراكز بيانات غوغل،
at least the ones that have people in them.
على الأقل تلك التي يوجد ناس بداخلها.
But I came up with my estimate,
لكن قمت بتوقعاتي،
which I felt pretty good about,
والتي كان إحساسي جيدا حيالها،
that was about 10 exabytes of data
كانت حوالي 10 إكسابايت من البيانات
across all of Google's operations,
على امتداد كل أعمال غوغل،
and then another maybe five exabytes or so
وتقريبا 5 إكسابايت أخرى
of offline storage in tape drives,
على كل أقراص التخزين الغير متصلة بالانترنت،
which it turns out Google is
والتي اتضح بأن غوغل
about the world's largest consumer of.
هي أكبر مستهلك في العالم لها.
So I came up with this estimate, and this is
لقد استنتجت هذه التوقعات وهي
a staggering amount of data.
كمية مذهلة من البيانات.
It's quite a bit more than any other organization
إنها تقريبًا أكثر من بيانات أي مؤسسة أخرى
in the world has, as far as we know.
في العالم، على حد علمنا.
There's a couple of other contenders,
هناك عدد من المنافسين الآخرين،
especially everyone always thinks of the NSA.
خاصة لمن يفكر دائمًا في الـ NSA.
But using some of these same methods,
باستخدام مثل بعض هذه الطرق،
we can look at the NSA's data centers,
بإمكاننا النظر إلى مراكز بيانات الـ NSA،
and figure out, you know, we don't know what's going on there,
ونخمن، تعلمون، نحن لا نعرف ماذا يحدث هناك بالفعل،
but it's pretty clear that their operation
لكن من الواضح جدًا أن أعمالهم
is not the size of Google's.
ليست بحجم غوغل.
Adding all of this up, I came up with
بعد أن جمعت كل هذا، توصلت إلى
the other thing that we can answer, which is,
حل للسؤال الذي نريد الإجابة عليه والذي كان،
how many punch cards would this take?
كم بطاقة مثقبة ستتحمل كل هذه البيانات؟
And so a punch card can hold
باعتبار أن البطاقة المثقبة تحتوي
about 80 characters,
على 80 رمزا،
and you can fit about 2,000 or so cards into a box,
وبالإمكان إدخال حوالي 2000 بطاقة في صندوق،
and you put them in, say,
ثم وضعها، مثلًا،
my home region of New England,
في المدينة التي جئت منها، نيو إنغلاند،
it would cover the entire region
ستغطي المدينة بأكملها
up to a depth of a little less than five kilometers,
إلى ارتفاع أقل بقليل من 5 كيلومتر،
which is about three times deeper
والذي يعتبر أكبر بثلاث مرات
than the glaciers during the last ice age
من الطبقة الجليدية في العصر الجليدي
about 20,000 years ago.
قبل 20000 سنة.
So this is impractical, but I think
سيكون هذا غير عملي، لكن أعتقد
that's about the best answer I could come up with.
أن هذا هو أفضل جواب ممكن أن آتي به.
And I posted it on my website. I wrote it up.
لذلك كتبته في موقعي.
And I didn't expect to get an answer from Google,
ولم أكن أتوقع أن يأتيني الرد من غوغل،
because of course they've been so secretive,
لأنهم بالطبع متحفظون جدًا،
they didn't answer of my questions,
لم يجيبون عن أسئلتي،
and so I just put it up and said,
لذلك كتبت الجواب ثم قلت،
well, I guess we'll never know.
حسنًا، أعتقد أننا لن نعلم أبدًا.
But then a little while later
لكن بعدها بفترة قصيرة
I got a message, a couple weeks later, from Google,
وصلتني رسالة، بعدها بعدة أسابيع، من غوغل
saying, hey, someone here has an envelope for you.
تقول، لدينا مغلف لك.
So I go and get it, open it up,
ذهبت واستلمته، ثم فتحته،
and it's punch cards. (Laughter)
لقد كانت بطاقات مثقبة. (ضحك)
Google-branded punch cards.
بطاقات مثقبة عليها شعار غوغل.
And on these punch cards, there are a bunch of holes,
وعلى هذه البطاقات المثقبة كانت هناك مجموعة من الثقوب،
and I said, thank you, thank you,
فقلت لهم، شكرًا لكم، شكرًا لكم،
okay, so what's on here?
حسنًا، ماذا لدينا هنا؟
So I get some software and start reading it,
جلبت بعض البرامج وبدأت في قراءتها،
and scan them, and it turns out
وتحليلها، وتبيّن أنها
it's a puzzle.
أحجية.
There's a bunch of code,
هناك عدد من الشفرات،
and I get some friends to help,
طلبت المساعدة من بعض الأصدقاء،
and we crack the code, and then inside that is another code,
وقمنا بتحليل الشفرة، فوجدنا بداخلها شفرة أخرى،
and then there are some equations,
بعدها هناك بعض المعادلات،
and then we solve those equations,
قمنا بحلها،
and then finally out pops a message from Google
وفي النهائية ظهرت رسالة من غوغل
which is their official answer to my article,
وقد كانت الرد الرسمي لهم على مقالي،
and it said, "No comment."
تقول: " لا تعليق."
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك) (تصفيق)
And I love calculating these kinds of things,
أحب حساب مثل هذه الأشياء،
and it's not that I love doing the math.
ليس ذلك لأني أحب الحساب.
I do a lot of math,
أنا أقوم بالكثير من الحسابات،
but I don't really like math for its own sake.
لكني لا أحب الحساب لذاته.
What I love is that it lets you take
ما أحبه هو أنها تجعلك تأخذ
some things that you know,
أشياء تعرفها،
and just by moving symbols around on a piece of paper,
وفقط بتحريك الرموز على قطعة من الورق،
find out something that you didn't know
تتوصل إلى معرفة شيء لم تكن تعرفه
that's very surprising.
وذلك مفاجئ جدًا.
And I have a lot of stupid questions,
تصلني الكثير من الأسئلة الغبية،
and I love that math gives the power
وأحب كون الحساب يمنحني القوة
to answer them sometimes.
لأجيب عليها أحيانًا.
And sometimes not.
وأحيانًا لا.
This is a question I got from a reader,
هذا سؤال وصلني من أحد القراء،
an anonymous reader,
بدون هوية،
and the subject line just said, "Urgent,"
وعنوانه كان فقط، "عاجل،"
and this was the entire email:
وهذا هو نص الرسالة:
"If people had wheels and could fly,
"لو كان للبشر عجلات ويستطيعون الطيران،
how would we differentiate them from airplanes?"
كيف سنفرق بينهم وبين الطائرات؟"
Urgent. (Laughter)
عاجل. (ضحك)
And I think there are some questions
أعتقد أن هناك بعض الأسئلة
that math just cannot answer.
لا يقدر الحساب على حلها.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)